The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: We introduced
the data last time.
These were some
macroeconomic variables
that can be used for forecasting
the economy in terms of growth
and factors such as
inflation or unemployment.
The case note goes through
analyzing just three
of these economic time
series-- the unemployment rate,
the federal funds rate,
and a measure of the CPI,
or Consumer Price Index.
When one fits a vector
autoregression model
to this data, it turns
out that the roots
of the characteristic polynomial
are 1.002, then 0.9863.
And you recall when our
discussion of vector
autoregressive models, there's
a characteristic equation
sort of in matrix
form, the determinant
is just like the univariate
autoregressive case.
And in order for the process
to be invertible, basically,
the roots of the
characteristic polynomial
need to be less
than 1 in magnitude.
In this implementation of the
vector autoregression model,
the characteristic
roots are the inverses
of the characteristic roots
that we've been discussing.
So anyway, this particular fit
of the vector autoregression
model suggests that the
process is non-stationary.
And so one should be
considering different series
to model this as a
stationary time series.
But in terms of interpreting
the regression model,
one can see-- to accommodate
the non-stationarity,
we can take differences
of all the series
and fit the vector
autoregression
to the difference series.
So one way of eliminating any
non-stationarity in time series
models, basically
eliminate the random walk
aspect of the processes, is to
be modeling first differences.
And so doing that with
this series-- let's see.
Here is just a graph of
the time series properties
of the difference series.
So with our original series, we
take differences and eliminate
missing values in this R code.
And this
autocorrelation function
shows us basically
the correlations
and autocorrelations
of individual series
and the cross-correlations
across the different series.
So along the diagonals are
the autocorrelation function.
And one can see
that every series
is correlation one with itself.
But then at the first
lag, positive for the Fed
funds and the CPI measure.
And there's also some
cross-correlations
that are strong.
And whether or not a
correlation is strong or not
depends upon how much
uncertainty there
is in our estimate
of the correlation.
And these dashed
lines here correspond
to plus or minus two standard
deviations of the correlation
coefficient when the correlation
coefficient is equal to 0.
So any correlations that sort
of go beyond those bounds
is statistically significant.
The partial autocorrelation
function is graphed here.
And let's say our
time series problem
set goes through some discussion
of the partial autocorrelation
coefficients and the
interpretation of those.
The partial autocorrelation
coefficients
are the correlation
between one variable
and the lag of another
after explaining
for all lower degree lags.
So it's like the incremental
correlation of a variable
with a lag term that exists.
And so if we are actually
fitting regression models where
we include extra lags
of a given variable,
that partial
autocorrelation coefficient
is essentially the correlation
associated with the addition
of the final lagged variable.
So here, we can see that
each of these series
is quite strongly
correlated with itself.
But there are also
some cross-correlations
with, like, the unemployment
rate and the Fed funds rate.
Basically, the Fed
funds rate tends
to go down when the
unemployment rate goes up.
And so this data is
indicating the association
between these
macroeconomic variables
and the evidence
of that behavior.
In terms of modeling the
actual structural relations
between these, we need
several, up to about 10
or 12 variables more
than these three.
And then one can have
a better understanding
of the drivers of various
macroeconomic features.
But this sort of
illustrates the use
of these methods with this
reduced variable case.
Let me also go
down here and just
comment on the unemployment
rate or the Fed funds rate.
When fitting these vector
autoregressive models
with the packages
that exist in R,
they give us output which
provides the specification
of each of the
autoregressive models
for the different dependent
variables, the different series
of the process.
And so here is the case of the
regression model for Fed funds
as a function of
unemployment rate lagged,
Fed funds rate lagged,
and CPI lagged.
These are all on
the different scale.
When you're looking at
these results, what's
important is
basically how strong
the signal-to-noise
ratio is for estimating
these autoregressive
parameters, vector
autoregressive parameters.
And so with the Fed funds,
you can look at the t values.
And t values that
are larger than 2
are certainly quite significant.
And you can see that basically
when the unemployment rate
coefficient is a negative
0.71, so if the unemployment
rate goes up, we expect to
see the Fed rate going down
the next month.
And the Fed funds rate for the
lag 1 has a t value of 7.97.
So these are now models
on the differences.
So if the Fed funds
rate was increased
last month or last quarter, it's
likely to be increased again.
And that's partly a factor
of how slow the economy is
in reacting to changes
and how the Fed doesn't
want to shock the economy with
large changes in their policy
rates.
Another thing to notice here
is that there's actually
a negative coefficient
on the lag 2
Fed funds term, a negative 0.17.
And in interpreting
these kinds of models,
I think it's helpful
just to think of,
if you have Fed
funds sub t, that's
equal to minus 0.71 times the
unemployment rate at t minus 1.
And then we have plus 0.37 times
the Fed funds, so t minus 1.
And this is delta.
And then minus 1.8
times the Fed funds.
So t minus 2.
In interpreting
these coefficients,
notice that these
two terms correspond
to 0.19 times the Fed funds
change 1 lag ago plus 0.18
times the change in that rate.
So when you see
multiple lags coming
into play in these models,
the interpretation of them
can be made by considering
different transformations
essentially of the
underlying variables.
In this form, you can see
that OK, the Fed funds
tends to change the way it
changed the previous month.
But it also may change
depending on the double change
in the previous month.
So there's a degree of
acceleration in the Fed funds
that is being captured here.
So the interpretation
of these models
sometimes requires some care.
This kind of analysis,
I find it quite useful.
So let's push on
to the next topic.
So today's topics are going
to begin with a discussion
of cointegration.
Cointegration is a major topic
in time series analysis, which
is dealing with the analysis
of non-stationary time series.
And in the previous
discussion, we
addressed
non-stationarity of series
by taking first
differences to eliminate
that non-stationarity.
But we may be losing
some information
with that differencing.
And cointegration
provides a framework
within which we
characterize all available
information for
statistical modeling,
in a very systematic way.
So let's introduce the
context within which
cointegration is relevant.
It's relevant when we
have a stochastic process,
a multivariate
stochastic process, which
is integrated of some order d.
And to be integrated
of order d means
that if we take the
d-th difference,
then that d-th
difference is stationary.
So and if you look
at a time series
and you plot that over time,
well, OK, a stationary time
series we know should be
something that basically
has a constant mean over time.
There's some steady
mean which that has.
And the variability
is also constant.
With some other time series,
it might increase linearly
over time.
And a series that increases
linearly over time, well,
if you take first
differences, that
tends to take out
that linear trend.
If there are higher order
differencing is required, then
that means that there's some
curvature, quadratic say,
that may exist in the data
that is being taken out.
So this differencing is required
to result in stationarity.
If the process does have vector
autoregressive representation
in spite of its
non-stationarity,
then it can be represented by
a polynomial lag of the x's is
equal to white noise epsilon.
And the polynomial
phi of L going
to have a factor term
in there of 1 minus L,
basically the first
difference to the d power.
So if taking these the
d-th order difference
reduces it to
stationarity, then we
can express this vector
autoregression in this way.
So the phi star of L
basically represents
the stationary vector
autoregressive process
on the d-th difference series.
Now, as it says here, each
of the component series
may be non-stationary and
integrated, say of order one.
But the process itself may
not be jointly integrated.
In that it may be that there
are linear combinations
of our multivariate series
which are stationary.
And so these linear
combinations basically
represent the stationary
features of the process.
And those features can be
apparent without looking
at differences.
So in a sense, if
you just focused
on differences of these
non-stationary multivariate
series, you would be
losing out on information
of the stationary structure
of contemporaneous components
of the multivariate series.
And so cointegration
deals with this situation
where some linear combinations
of the multivariate series
in fact are stationary.
So how do we represent
that mathematically?
Well, we say that this
multivariate time series
process is cointegrated if
there exists an m-vector beta
such that, defining linear
weights on the x's, and
beta prime X_t is a
stationary process.
The cointegration vector of
beta can be scaled arbitrarily.
So it's common
practice, if one has
an interest, some primary
interest, perhaps,
in the first component
series of process,
to set that equal to 1.
And the expression
basically says
that our time t value
of the first series
is related in a stationary
way to a linear combination
of the other m minus 1 series.
And this is a long-run
equilibrium type relationship.
How does this arise?
Well, it arises in many, many
ways in economics and finance.
The term structure of interest
rates, purchase power parity.
In the terms structure
of interest rates,
basically the differences
between yields
on interest rates over
different maturities,
those differences
might be stationary.
The overall level of interest
might not be stationary,
but the spreads ought
to be stationary.
The purchase power parity
in foreign exchange,
if you look at the
value of currencies
for different countries,
basically different countries
ought to be able to purchase
the same goods for roughly
the same price.
And so if there are
disparities in currency values,
purchase power parity suggests
that things will revert back
to some norm where everybody
is paying on average over time
the same amount for
different goods.
Otherwise, there
would be arbitrage.
Money demand, covered
interest rate parity,
law of one price,
spot and futures.
Let me show you
another example that
will be in the case
study for this chapter.
View, full screen.
Let's think about
energy futures.
In fact, next Tuesday's
talk from Morgan Stanley
is going to be an expert in
commodity futures and options.
And that should be
very interesting.
Anyway, here, I'm
looking at energy futures
from the Energy
Information Administration.
Actually, for this
course, trying
to get data that's freely
available to students
is one of the things we do.
So this data is actually
available from the Energy
Information Administration
of the government, which
is now open, so I guess
that'll be updated over time.
But basically these
energy futures
are traded on the Chicago
Mercantile Exchange.
And basically CL is crude,
West Texas intermediate crude,
light crude, which we have
here, a time series from 2006
to basically yesterday.
And you can see how at the
start of the period around $60
and then went up
to close to $140,
and then it dropped
down to around $40.
And it's been hovering
around $100 lately.
The second series here is
gasoline, RBOB gasoline.
Always have to look this up.
This is that reformulated blend
stock for oxygenated blending
gasoline.
Anyway, futures on this product
are traded at the CME as well.
And then heating oil.
And what's happening
with these data
is that we have basically
a refinery which processes
crude oil as an input.
And it basically
refines it, distills it,
and generates outputs, which
include heating oil, gasoline,
and various other things
like jet fuel and others.
So if we're looking
at the prices,
the futures prices of, say,
gasoline and heating oil,
relating those to crude
oil, well, certainly,
the cost of producing these
products should depend
on the cost of the input .
So I've got in the next plot,
a translation of these futures
contracts into their
price per barrel.
Turns out crude is quoted
in dollars per barrel.
And the gasoline heating
oil are in cents per gallon.
So one multiplies.
There are 42
gallons in a barrel.
So you multiply those
previous years by 42.
And this shows the plot of
the prices of the futures
where we're looking at
essentially the same units
of output relative to input.
And what's evident here is that
while the futures for gasoline,
the blue, is consistently above
the green, the input, and same
for heating oil.
And those vary depending
on which is greater.
So if we look at the
difference between, say,
the price of the heating
oil future and the crude oil
future, what does
that represent?
That's the spread in value of
the output minus the input.
Ray?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] cost
of running the refinery?
PROFESSOR: So cost of refining.
So let's look at, say,
heating oil minus CL and, say,
this RBOB minus CL.
So it's cost of refining.
What else could
be a factor here?
AUDIENCE: Supply and demand
characteristics [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Definitely.
Supply and demand.
If one product is demanded
a lot more than another.
Supply and demand.
Anything else?
AUDIENCE: Maybe for
the outputs, if you
were to find the difference
between the outputs,
it would be something cyclical.
For example, in the
winter, heating oil
is going to get far more
valuable as gasoline,
because people drive less
and people demand more
for heating homes.
PROFESSOR: Absolutely.
That's a very significant
factor with these.
There are seasonal effects
that drive supply and demand.
And so we can put
seasonal effects in there
as affecting supply and demand.
But certainly, you might expect
to see seasonal structure here.
Anything else?
Put on your traders hat.
Profit, yes.
The refinery needs
to make some profit.
So there has to be some
level of profit that's
acceptable and appropriate.
So we have all these
things driving basically
these differences.
Let's just take a look
at those differences.
These are actually
called the crack spreads.
Cracking in the
business of refining
is basically the
breaking down of oil
into components, products.
And on the top is the
gasoline crack spread.
And the bottom is the
heating oil crack spread.
And one can see
that as time series,
these actually look stationary.
There certainly doesn't appear
to be a linear trend up.
But there are, of course, many
factors that could affect this.
So with that as motivation, how
would we model such a series?
So let's go back to
our lecture here.
All right, View, full size.
This is going to be a
very technical discussion,
but it's, at the end of the day,
I think fairly straightforward.
And the objective
actually of this lecture
is to provide an introduction
to the notation here, which
should make it seem like it's a
very straightforward derivation
process of these models.
So let's begin with just a recap
of the vector autoregressive
model of order p.
This is the extension of
the univariate case where
we have a vector C of
constants, m constants,
and matrices phi_1 to
phi_p corresponding
to basically how the
autoregression of one series
depends on all the other series.
And then there's multivariate
white noise eta_t,
which has mean 0 and some
covariance structure in it.
And the stationarity-- if
this series were stationary,
then the determinant of
this matrix polynomial
would have roots outside the
unit circle for complex z.
And if it's not stationary,
then some of those roots
will be on the unit
circle or beyond.
So let's actually go to
that non-stationary case
and suppose that the process
is integrated of order one.
So if we were to take
first differences,
we would have stationarity.
Well, the derivation
of the model
proceeds by converting the
original vector autoregressive
equation into an
equation that's mostly
relating to differences but
with also some extra terms.
So let's begin the process
by just subtracting
the lagged value of
the multivariate vector
from the original series.
So we subtract X_(t-1)
from both sides,
and we get delta X_t is equal to
C plus phi_1 minus I_m X_(t-1)
plus the rest.
So that's a very simple step.
We're just subtracting the
lagged multivariate series
from both sides.
Now, what we want
to do is convert
the second term in the middle
line into a difference term.
So what do we do?
Well, we can subtract and add
phi_1 minus I_m times X_(t-2).
If we do that,
subtract and add that,
we then get the delta X_t is
C plus a multiple of delta
X_(t-1) plus this
multiple of X_(t-2).
So we basically
reduced the equations
to differences in
the first two terms
or in the current
series and the lagged.
But then we have the original
series for lags t minus 2.
We can continue this
process with the third.
And then at the
end of the day, we
end up getting this equation
for the difference of the series
is equal to a constant
plus a matrix multiple
of the first difference
multivariate series,
plus another matrix times
the second difference,
all the way down to
the p-th difference,
or the p minus first difference.
But at the end,
we're left with terms
at p lags that have no
differences in them.
So we've been able to
represent this series
as an autoregressive
function of differences.
But there's also a term on
the undifferenced series
at the end that's left over.
And or this argument
can actually
proceed by eliminating
differences in the reverse way,
starting with the
p-th lag and going up.
And one then can represent
this as delta X_t
is C plus some
matrix times just the
lagged series plus various
matrices times the differences
going back p minus 1 lags.
And so at the end of
the day, this model
basically for delta
X_t is a constant
plus a matrix times the
previous lagged series
or the first lag of the
multivariate time series,
plus various autoregressive
lags of the differenced series.
So these notes give you
the formulas for those,
and they're very easy to
verify if you go through them
one by one.
And when we look at this
expression for the model,
this expresses the
stochastic process model
for the difference series.
This difference
series is stationary.
We've eliminated
the non-stationarity
in the process.
So that means the
right-hand side
has to be stationary as well.
And so while the terms which
are matrix multiples of lags
of the differenced
series, those are
going to be stationary
because we're just
taking lags of the
stationary multivariate time
series, the difference series.
But this pi X_t term has
to be stationary as well.
So this pi X_t contains
the cointegrating terms.
And fitting a sort of
cointegrated vector
autoregression model involves
identifying this term, pi X_t.
And given that the original
series had unit roots,
it has to be the case that
pi, the matrix, is singular.
So it's basically
a transformation
of the data that
eliminates that unit
root in the overall series.
So the matrix pi
is of reduced rank,
and it's either rank
zero, in which case
there's no cointegrating
relationships,
or its rank is less than m.
And the matrix pi does
define the cointegrating
relationships.
Now, these cointegrating
relationships
are the relationships in the
process that are stationary.
And so basically there's
a lot of information
in that multivariate series
with contemporaneous values
of the series.
There is stationary structure
at every single time
point, which can be the
target of the modeling.
So this matrix pi is
of rank r less than m.
And so it can be expressed
as basically alpha beta
prime, where these matrices
are of rank r, alpha and beta.
And the columns of beta define
linearly independent vectors
which cointegrate x.
And the decomposition
of pi isn't unique.
You can basically, for any
invertible r by r matrix g,
define another set of
cointegrating relationships.
So in the linear algebra
structure of these problems,
there's basically an
r-dimensional space
where the process is
stationary, and how
you define the coordinate system
in that space is up to you
or subject to some choice.
So how do we estimate
these models?
Well, rather nice result
of Sims, Stock, and Watson.
Actually, Sims,
Christopher Sims,
he got the Nobel Prize a
few years ago for his work
in econometrics.
And so this is a rather
significant work that he did.
Anyway, he, together
with Stock and Watson,
prove that if you're estimating
a vector autoregression model,
then the least squares
estimator of the original model
is basically sufficient
to do an analysis
of this cointegrated vector
autoregression process.
The parameter estimates
from just fitting
the vector autoregression are
consistent for the underlying
parameters.
And they have
asymptotic distributions
that are identical to those of
maximum likelihood estimators.
And so what ends up happening
is the least squares estimates
of the vector autoregression
parameters lead
to an estimation
of the pi matrix.
And the constraints on the pi
matrix which are basically pi
is of reduced rank, those
will hold asymptotically.
So let's just go back
to the equation before,
to see if that
looks familiar here.
So what that work says
is that if we basically
fit the linear regression
model regressing the difference
series on the lag of the series
plus lags of differences,
the least squares estimates
of these underlying parameters
will give us asymptotically
efficient estimates
of this overall process.
So we don't need to use any new
tools to specify these models.
There's an advanced literature
on estimation methods
for these models.
Johansen does describe
maximum likelihood estimation
when the innovation terms
are normally distributed.
And that methodology applies
reduced rank regression
methodology and
yields tests for what
the rank is of the
cointegrating relationship.
And these methods are
implemented in our packages.
Let's see.
Let me just go back now
to the-- so let's see.
The case study on
the crack spread data
actually goes through sort of
testing for non-stationarity
in these underlying series.
And actually, why don't
I just show you that?
Let's go back here.
If you can see this, for
the crack spread data,
looking at the
crude oil futures,
basically the crude oil
future can be evaluated
to see if it's non-stationary.
And there's this augmented
Dickey-Fuller test
for non-stationarity.
And it basically has a null
hypothesis that the model
or the series is non-stationary,
or it has a unit root,
versus the alternative
that it doesn't.
And so testing that
null hypothesis
that it's non-stationary
yields a p-value of 0.164
for CLC1, the first
nearest contract,
near month contract of
the futures for crude.
And so the data
suggests that crude
has a distribution that's
non-stationary, integrated
order 1.
And the HOC1 also basically
has a test for-- p-value
for non-stationarity of 0.3265.
So we can't reject
non-stationarity or unit root
in those series with
these test statistics.
In analyzing the data, this
suggests that we basically
need to accommodate that
non-stationarity when
we specify the models.
Let me just see if
there's some results here.
For this series,
actually the case notes
will go through actually
conducting this Johansen
procedure for
testing for the rank
of the cointegrated process.
And that test basically has
different test statistic
for testing whether the rank is
0, 1, less than or equal to 1,
or less than or equal to 2.
And one can see that
there's marginal-- the test
statistic is almost
significant at the 10% level
for the overall series.
It's not significant
for the rank
being less than or equal to 1.
And so these results, it
doesn't suggest there's
strong non-stationarity.
But certainly with
that non-stationarity
is no more than rank
one for the series.
And the eigenvector
corresponding
to the stationary
relationship is
given by these coefficients
of 1 on the crude oil future,
1.3 on the RBOB and minus
1.7 on the heating oil.
So what this suggests
is that there's
considerable variability in
these energy futures contracts.
What appears to be stationary
is some linear combination
of crude plus gasoline
minus heating oil.
And in terms of why does
it combine that way,
well, there are all
kinds of factors
that we went through-- cost of
refining, supply and demand,
seasonality, which
affect things.
And so when analyzed, sort
of ignoring seasonality,
these would be the linear
combinations that appear
to be stationary over time.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Why did you
choose to use the futures
prices as opposed to the spot?
And how did you combine the
data with actual [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: I chose this
because if refiners are wanting
to hedge their risks, then they
will go to the futures market
to hedge those.
And so working with
these data, one
can then consider problems of
hedging refinery production
risks.
And so that's why.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK, well, the Energy
Information Administration
provides historical data
which gives the first month,
the second month, the third
month available for each
of these contracts.
And so I chose the
first month contract
for each of these features.
Those 10 are the most liquid.
Depending on what
one is hedging,
one would use perhaps
longer periods for those.
There's some very
nice finance problems
dealing with hedging,
hedging these kinds of risks,
and as well as trading
these kinds of risk.
Traders can try to exploit
short term movements in these.
Anyway, I'll let you
look through these,
the case note later.
And it does provide some detail
on the coefficient estimates.
And one can basically
get a handle
on how these things
are being specified.
So let's go back.
The next topic I want to cover
is linear state-space models.
It turns out that many
of these time series
models appropriate in
economics and finance
can be expressed as a
linear state-space model.
I'm going to introduce the
general notation first and then
provide illustrations
of this general notation
with a number of
different examples.
So the formulation is we have
basically an observation vector
at time t, y_t.
This is our multivariate time
series that we're modeling.
Now, I've chosen it
to be k-dimensional
for the observations.
There's an underlying
state vector
that's of m dimensions,
which basically characterizes
the state of the
process at time t.
There's an observation error
vector at time t, epsilon_t.
So it's k by 1 as well,
corresponding to y.
And there's a state transition
innovation error vector,
which is n by 1,
which actually can
be different from m, the
dimension of the state vector.
So we have-- in the state
space specification,
we're going to specify
two equations, one
for how the states evolve
over time and another for how
the observations or
measurements evolve,
depending on the
underlying states.
So let's first focus
on a state equation
which describes how
the state progresses
from the state at time t to
the state at time t plus 1.
Because this is a linear
state-space model,
basically the state
at t plus 1 is
going to be some linear
function of the states at time
t plus some noise.
And that noise is
given by eta_t,
being independent identically
distributed white noise,
or normally distributed
with some covariance matrix
Q_t, positive definite.
And R_t is some
linear transformation
of those, which
characterize the uncertainty
in the particular states.
So there's a great
deal of flexibility
here in how things
depend on each other.
And right now, it will appear
just like a lot of notation.
But as we see it
in different cases,
you'll see how these
terms come into play.
And they're very
straightforward.
So we're considering simple
linear transformations
of the states plus noise.
And then the observation
equation or measurement
equation is a linear
transformation
of the underlying
states plus noise.
So the matrix Z_t is the
observation coefficients
matrix.
And the noise or innovations
epsilon_t are, we'll assume,
independent
identically distributed
normal, multivariate
normal random variables
with some covariance matrix H_t.
To be fully general,
the subscript t
means the covariance
can depend on time t.
It doesn't have to, but it can.
These two equations
can be written together
in a joint equation where
we see that the underlying
state at time t, s, gets
transformed with T sub t
to the state at t plus 1 plus
residual innovation term.
And the observation equation
y_t is Z_t s_t plus that.
So we're representing how
the states evolve over time
and how the observations
depend on the underlying
states in this joint equation.
And the structure of
basically this sort
of linear function of states
plus error, the error term u_t
here is normally distributed
with covariance matrix omega,
which has this structure.
It's a block diagonal.
We have the covariance
of the epsilons as the H.
And the covariance of R_t
eta_t is R_t Q_t R_t transpose.
So you may recall when we
take a covariance matrix
of linear function of random
variables given by a matrix,
then it's that linear function
R times the covariance matrix
times the transpose.
So that term comes into play.
So let's see how a
capital asset pricing
model with time-varying
betas can be represented
as a linear state-space model.
You'll recall, we discussed
this model a few lectures ago,
where we have the excess
return of a given stock, r_t,
is a linear function of the
excess return of the market
portfolio, r_(m,t), plus error.
What we're going to do now
is extend that previous model
by adding time dependence, t,
to the regression parameters.
The alpha is not a constant.
It is going to vary by time.
And the beta is also
going to very by time.
And how will they vary by time?
Well, we're going to
assume that the alpha_t is
a Gaussian random walk.
And the beta is also a
Gaussian random walk.
And with that set up, we
have the following expression
for the state equation.
OK, the state equation, which
is just the unknown parameters--
it's the alpha and the
beta at given time t.
The state at time
t gets adjusted
to the state at time t plus 1
by just adding these random walk
terms to it.
So it's a very simple process.
We have the identity
times the previous state
plus the identity times this
vector of these innovations.
So s_(t+1) is equal to
T_t s_t plus R_t eta_t,
where this matrix, T sub
t and R sub t are trivial;
they're just the identity.
And eta_t has a
covariance matrix
which is just given by
Q_t, sigma squared nu,
sigma squared epsilon.
This is a complex way, perhaps,
of representing this model.
But it puts this simple model
into that linear state-space
framework.
Now, the observation equation
is given by this expression
defining the Z_t matrix as the
unit element and r_(m,t) So
it's basically a row vector, or
a row matrix, one-row matrix.
And epsilon_t is the
white noise process.
Now, putting these
equations together,
we basically have the equation
for the state transition
and the observation
equation together.
We have this form for that.
So now, let's
consider a second case
of linear regression
models where
we have a time varying beta.
In a way, this case
we just looked at
is a simple case of that.
But let's look at
a more general case
where we have p independent
variables, which
could be time-varying.
So we have a
regression model almost
as we've considered
it previously.
y_t is equal to x_t transpose
beta_t plus epsilon_t.
The difference now is our
regression coefficients
beta are allowed to
change over time.
How do they change over time?
Well, we're going to
assume that those also
follow independent random
walks with variances
of the random walks that
may depend on the component.
So the joint
state-space equation
here is given by the identity
times s_t plus eta_t.
That's basically the random
walk process for the underlying
regression parameters.
And y_t is equal
to x_t transpose
times the same regression
parameters plus the observation
error.
I guess needless to say, if we
consider the special case where
the random walk
process is degenerate
and they're basically
steps of size zero,
then we get the normal linear
regression model coming out
of this.
If we were to be specifying
the linear state-space
implementation of this model and
consider successive estimates
of the model
parameters over time,
then these equations would
give us recursive estimates
for updating
regressions as we add
additional values to the
data, additional observations
to the data.
Let's look at autoregressive
models of order p.
The autoregressive model of
order p for a univariate time
series has the setup given here.
It's a polynomial
lag of the response
variable y_t is equal to
the innovation epsilon_t.
And we can define
the state vector
to be equal to the vector of
p values, p successive values
of the process.
And so we basically
get a combination
here of the observation equation
and state equation joining
where basically
one of the states
is actually equal
to the observation.
And basically, with
this definition
for a state of the vector
at the next time point t,
that is equal to this
linear transformation
of the lagged state vector
plus that innovation term.
I dropped the mic.
So the notation here
shows the structure
for how this linear
state-space model is evolving.
Basically, the
observation equation
is the linear
combination of the five
multiples of lags of the
values plus the residual.
And the previous
lags of the states
are just simply the identities
times those values, shifted.
So it's a very simple structure
for the autoregressive process
as a linear state-space model.
We have, as I was just saying,
for the transition matrix T sub
t, this matrix and the
observation equation
is essentially picking out
the first element of the state
vector, which has no
measurement error.
So that simplifies that.
The moving average
model of order q
could also be expressed as
a linear state-space model.
Remember, the
moving average model
is one where our response
variable, y, is simply
some linear combination
of innovations,
q past innovations.
And this state
vector, if we consider
the state vector just
being basically q
lags of the innovations,
then the transition
of those underlying states is
given by this expression here.
And we have a state equation,
an observation equation,
which has these forms for these
various transition matrices
and for how the innovation
terms are related.
Let me just finish
up with example
showing with the autoregressive
moving average model.
And many years ago,
it was actually
very difficult to
specify the estimation
methods for autoregressive
moving average models.
But the implementation
of these models
as linear state-space models
facilitated that greatly.
And with the ARMA model,
the setup basically
is a combination of
the autoregressive
moving average processes.
We have an
autoregression of the y's
is equal to a moving
average of the residuals
or the innovations.
And it's convenient in the setup
for linear state-space models
to define the dimension m,
which is the maximum of p and q
plus 1, and think of having
basically a possibly m order
polynomial lag for each
of those two series.
And we can basically
constrain those values
to be 0 if m is greater than
p or m is greater than q.
And Harvey, in a very
important work in '93,
actually defined a particular
state-space representation
for this process.
And I guess it's
important to know
that with these linear
state-space models,
we're dealing with
characterizing structure
in m-dimensional space.
There's often some choice in how
you represent your underlying
states.
You can basically
re-parametrize the models
by considering invertible
linear transformations
of the underlying states.
So let me go back here.
In expressing the state
equation generally
is T sub t s_t plus R_t eta_t.
This matrix T sub t
and st-- basically s_t
can be replaced by a linear
transformation of s_t,
so long as we multiply
the T sub t by the inverse
of that transformation.
So there's flexibility
in the choice
of our linear state-space
specification.
And so there really are many
different equivalent linear
state-space models for a
given process depending
on exactly how you
define the states
and the underlying
transformation matrix T.
And the beauty of Harvey's
work was coming up
with a nice representation
for the states,
where we had very simple forms
for the various matrices.
And the lecture notes here
go through the derivation
of that for the ARMA process.
And this derivation
is-- I just want
to go through the
first case just
to highlight how
the argument goes.
We basically have this equation,
which is the original equation
for an ARMA(p,q) process.
And Harvey says, well,
define the first--
or the state at time t to
be equal to the observation
at time t.
If we do that, then how
does this equation relate
to the basically-- this is the
state at the next time point, t
plus 1, is equal to phi_1
times the state at time t,
plus a second state at time
t and a residual innovation
eta_t.
So by choosing the first state
to be the observation value
at that time, we can then
solve for the second state,
which is given by
this expression,
just by rewriting our model
equation in terms of s_(1,t),
s_(2,t) and eta_t.
So this s_(2,t) is this function
of the observations and eta_t.
So it's a very
simple specification
of the second state.
Just what is that
second state element
given this definition
of the first one?
And one can do this
process iteratively
getting rid of the
observations and replacing them
by underlying states.
And at the end of
the day, you end up
with this very simple form
for the transition matrix T.
Basically, the T has the
autoregressive components
as the first column
of the T matrix.
And this R matrix has
this vector of the moving
average components.
So it's a very nice way
to represent the model.
Coming up with it was something
very clever that he did.
But what one can see is
that this basic model where
you have the states
transitioning according
to a linear transformation of
the previous state plus error,
and the observation being some
function of the current states,
plus error or not, depending
on the formulation,
is the representation.
Now, with all of
these models, a reason
why linear state-space
modeling is in fact effective
is that their specification is
fully specified with the Kalman
filter.
So with this formulation of
linear state-space models,
the Kalman filter
as a methodology is
the recursive computation
of the probability density
functions for the underlying
states at basically
t plus 1 given
information up to time t,
as well as the joint
density of the future state
and the future observation at
t plus 1, given information up
to time t.
And also just the
marginal distribution
of the next observation given
the information up to time t.
So what I want to do is
just go through with you
how the Kalman filter is
implemented and defined.
And the implementation
of the Kalman filter
requires us to have some
notation that's a bit involved,
but we'll hopefully explain it
so it's very straightforward.
There are basically conditional
means of the states.
s sub t given t
is the mean value
of the state at time t given
the information up to time t.
If we condition
on t minus 1, then
it's the expectation
of the state
at time t given the
information up to t minus 1.
And then y t t minus
1 is the expectation
of the observation given
information up to t minus 1.
There's also
conditional covariances
and mean squared errors.
All these covariances
are determined by omegas.
The subscript corresponds to
states s, or observation y.
And basically, the
conditioning set
is either information up to
time t, t minus 1 or t minus 1
in the second case.
And we want to compute
basically the covariance matrix
of the states given whatever
the information is, information
up to time t, t minus 1.
So these covariance
matrices are the expectation
of the state minus
their expectation
under the conditioning times
the state minus the expectation
transpose.
That's the definition of
that covariance matrix.
So the different
definitions here
correspond to just
whether we're conditioning
on different information.
And then the observation
innovations or residuals
are the difference
between an observation y_t
and its estimate given
information up to t minus 1.
So the residuals in this process
are the innovation residuals,
one period ahead.
And the Kalman filter
consists of four steps.
We basically want to, first,
predict the state vector
one step ahead.
So given our estimate of the
state vector at time t minus 1,
we want to predict this
state vector at time t.
And we also want to
predict the observation
at time t given our estimate
at state vector time t minus 1.
And so at time t minus 1, we
can estimate these quantities.
[INAUDIBLE]
At t minus 1, we can
basically predict
what the state is going
to and predict what
the observation is going to be.
And we can estimate
how much error there's
going to be in those estimates,
by these covariance matrices.
The second step is
updating these predictions
to get our estimate of the state
given the observation at time t
and to update our uncertainty
about that state given
this new observation.
So basically, our estimate
of the state at time t
is an adjustment to our
estimate given information up
to t minus 1, plus a function of
the difference between what we
observed and what we predicted.
And this T_t function matrix is
called the filter gain matrix.
And basically, it
characterizes how
do we adjust our prediction
of the underlying state
depending on what happened.
So that's the
filter gain matrix.
So we actually do
gain information
with each observation about what
the new value of the process
is.
And that information
is characterized
by filter gain matrix.
You'll notice that
the uncertainty
in the state at time t, this
omega_s of t given t, that's
equal to the covariance
matrix given t minus 1.
So it's our beginning level
of uncertainty adjusted
by a term that tells us
how much information did we
get from that new information.
So notice that there's
a minus sign there.
We're basically
reducing our uncertainty
about the state given the
information in the innovation
that we now have observed.
Then, there's a
forecasting step which
is used to forecast the
state one period forward,
is simply given by this
linear transformation
of the previous state.
And we can also update
our covariance matrix
for future states given
the previous state
by applying this formula
which is a recursive formula
for estimating covariances.
So we have
forecasting algorithms
that are simple linear
functions of these estimates.
And then finally,
there's a smoothing step
which is characterizing
the conditional expectation
of underlying states, given
information in the whole time
series.
And so ordinarily with Kalman
filters, Kalman filters
are applied
sequentially over time
where one basically
is predicting ahead
one step, updating
that prediction,
predicting ahead another
step, updating the information
on the states.
And that overall
process is the process
of actually computing
the likelihood
function for these linear
state-space models.
And so the Kalman filter is
basically ultimately applied
for successive
forecasting of the process
but also for helping us identify
what the underlying model
parameters are using
maximum likelihood methods.
And so the likelihood function
for the linear state-space
model is basically the--
or the log-likelihood
is the log-likelihood of
the entire data series,
give the unknown parameters.
But that can be
expressed as the product
of the conditional distributions
of each successive observation,
given the history.
And so basically, the
likelihood of theta
is the likelihood of
the first observation
times the density of the
second observation given
the first times and so
forth for the whole series.
And so the likelihood
function is basically
a function of all these
terms that we were computing
with the Kalman filter.
And with the Kalman
filter, it basically
provides all the terms
necessary for this estimation.
If the error terms are
normally distributed,
then the means and
variances of these estimates
are in fact characterizing
the exact distributions
of the process.
Basically, we're taking--
if the innovation series are
all normal random
variables, then
the linear
state-space model, all
it's doing is taking linear
combinations of normals
for the underlying states and
for the actual observations.
And normal
distributions are fully
characterized by
their mean vectors
and covariance matrices.
And the Kalman
filter provides a way
to update these distributions
for all these features
of a model, the
underlying states
as well as the distributions
of the observations.
So that's a brief introduction
the Kalman filter.
Let's finish there.
Thank you.